Ogon Country is famous for its cliffs, which are home to villages embedded in the rock.
The oldest date from the 15th century.
Ten years ago,
It was Mali's top tourist destination.
But since 2016,
The region is infested with jihadists.
This area is the most dangerous in the country.
Here,
Neither the Malian military,
nor are the French military present.
Rare signs of security,
these roadblocks manned by armed men.
Modibo,
our driver,
knows the region well.
Previously,
He regularly drove tourists there.
These civilians control the entrance to Ogoniland.
On this road,
we pass several checkpoints.
Good morning,
How's it going
Jihadists regularly carry out ambushes here.
Then, each vehicle is searched to prevent it from entering the area.
Only the local population has the right to move freely.
Here is her top,
There is a training camp, hunters.
They are there,
they are in training,
here there.
These men are all wearing the outfits of Ozo hunters.
A secret brotherhood, the repository of esoteric knowledge, is respected by the population.
Their amulets and gris-gris are endowed with magical powers,
supposed to make them invisible and even protect them from bullets.
They are armed with knives and old hunting rifles.
These dozos formed themselves into militias.
Many villagers came to swell their ranks to fight against the jihadists.
All these dozos are part of the most powerful militia in the region,
Tanna Ambassagou.
Its members are estimated at around 1,000.
At its head,
Youssouf Toloba,
a man who is difficult to access.
He lives in the heart of the cliff to avoid assassination attempts.
It is Commander Martaud who will take us to him.
We're going to Akhashan,
We're going to go see where they attacked.
There's a lot of old times there.
With these men,
They constantly patrol the cliff.
A place they absolutely must control,
because it is the last bulwark against the jihadists.
The jihadists burned the villages.
More than
12 villages like this are burned.
They killed many people and then they burned the whole house,
the attics.
All animals,
They left with all the animals.
Hammer and his men only see their families three times a year.
Their village is only about twenty kilometers away.
We,
we don't stay in the city.
We can always stay in the forest.
Not three months,
four months,
even one day,
We are not in the villages.
Hammer is 25 years old.
He left high school ten years ago to become a dozo.
And take to the bush.
These militiamen are between 25 and 60 years old.
Farmers or shepherds,
all lived a peaceful life,
until the arrival of the jihadists.
We do this because we have no choice.
They destroyed the country.
I am a shepherd.
The jihadists took all our animals.
We have nothing left.
I was a student at the Koranic School.
They chased us away and burned all the Qurans.
There is no more mosque.
They took all the prayer mats.
They even took the stretchers used to carry the dead.
They didn't manage to destroy everything, because we are here.
But the state can't even be bothered to ask us what's going on.
That's normal.
Are we not part of the state,
we the land of Ogon.
Of course I do.
Today,
whatever happens,
We are engaged in war to the death and we will go to the end.
Exceptionally,
We were able to spend several days with these men who defend,
whatever the cost,
The land of Ogon,
this small territory in the Sahel.
The Sahel.
A strip of savannah and desert as large as Europe,
populated by 100 million inhabitants or sedentary farmers,
coexists with nomadic herders.
An area spanning 8 countries,
hit by terrorism.
Among the hardest hit,
Mali.
A coalition of jihadist groups, created in 2017 and placed under the banner of Al-Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb,
extends its grip on the center of the country.
Jihadists are trying to impose Sharia law on its inhabitants.
Facing them,
a corrupt Malian army,
poorly disciplined and under-equipped,
which still cannot be contained. The advance of the jihadists,
despite the deployment of 5,000 French soldiers in the Sahel,
came to support and train them.
Faced with the failures of a Malian state undermined by repeated coups,
entire territories are left abandoned.
To protect yourself,
Dogon civilians have formed self-defense groups.
The government does not arm us.
We are in our caves.
And when the jihadists pass,
We eliminate them and take their weapons.
The absence of a state reawakens old conflicts between farmers and herdsmen.
When the animals come down,
This is a time when there are also disputes around the rooms.
So, all the time,
These are conflicts.
Jihadists are taking advantage of these tensions to attract new recruits to their ranks.
We met four repentant people.
Everything you do must be validated by them.
Even if it doesn't suit you,
you have to do it.
Whether you like it or not,
They indoctrinate you.
The only country to have stopped the advance of jihadists in the Sahel.
Mauritania,
she hunts them on land,
as if in the air,
thanks to anti-guerrilla warplanes.
But also thanks to traditional methods,
camel-riding gendarmes collecting intelligence to the far reaches of the desert.
Good morning,
We're not going to ask you for a sheep.
We just need some information.
Immersion in a Sahel that has become the scene of a borderless jihad.
In Mali,
60%
Jihadist attacks are concentrated in the center of the country.
Ogoniland is now surrounded on all sides.
The cliff is a natural barrier.
It prevents jihadists based in the plain from accessing the plateaus and its large towns,
like Bandiagara.
Sévare or Mopti,
in the rock face,
The militia of a naam Basagou is the only one to resist.
Commander Marteau and his men operate in a hostile environment.
The temperature is around 45 degrees in the shade.
Vegetation is sparse.
To refuel,
The Dozos can count on the support of villagers who go to meet them in the heights,
like Bashir.
Honor,
consideration,
Glory to you.
The greeting by placing the hand on the ground is a sign of deep respect.
Bachir came to bring food to the hunters.
A year ago,
He left Bamako and returned to his native region to help his community.
We want to drink.
Give them water.
Chief,
here is some water.
As we are hungry,
We haven't eaten since yesterday.
Yesterday,
after dinner,
We found nothing.
So we're hungry.
We're going to do a few things.
Yes.
Okay.
Good time.
Yes,
ok.
I'm counting on you.
But before having the meal...
So yes,
a guard there.
Hammer places lookouts around the bivouac.
Around thirty jihadist units are operating in the plain below.
The nearest one is a kilometer away as the crow flies.
SO,
for that,
we gave up.
So.
We're going to clean the guns here.
It was the army that gave you this, yes,
we found with the former.
We pulled the formerly,
they died.
The weapons were taken away.
All right.
These dozos receive no help,
nor of the Malian government,
nor of the French army.
Yes,
It's for the staff.
What position are you in?
Every time it reaches a crest,
Hammer calls Toloba.
The great leader of the militia,
to receive his instructions.
The first camp,
Yes,
Yes.
Okay,
ok,
THANKS.
Thank you so much.
It's okay.
So we can go to the fofotte
Here, the meal is sacred.
SO,
we take it in silence.
And there's no question of dropping his weapon.
Thank you so much.
About fifty units, like Marteau's, patrol the cliff.
Among them,
Toloba Mobile HQ.
This warlord is constantly on the move because he is a favorite target of jihadists.
This man,
who flees the media,
finally agreed to talk to us,
thanks to the insistence of an intermediary from Ogon.
Tell him that if I came here this morning...
It's thanks to you.
I had no intention of coming.
Even people from my village don't get the chance to meet me.
Ask them.
They see me when I pass,
but that's all.
Toloba left the Malian army 25 years ago to fight a Tuareg rebellion in northern Mali.
In 2016,
in the face of the advance of the jihadists,
he returns to Ogon country.
This is where they founded the Anna Militia in Basagou.
All the hunters you see here,
They are Malians.
There are no foreigners among them.
The government does not arm us.
We are in our caves.
And when the jihadists pass,
We eliminate them and take their weapons.
The army is not helping us.
France is not helping us.
Nobody helps us.
However,
local populations,
they,
They are with us.
Until today,
Toloba and his hunters manage to hold the cliff.
But the jihadists still managed to launch raids on the villages.
Since 2016,
in the surrounding area,
12 hamlets in the commune of Kassa were looted.
They burned all that.
They gathered the materials and burned them here.
They burned the kitchen matroles,
plus motorcycles,
the motorcycles are released.
The more animals,
They did everything with it.
The villagers were victims of the usual blackmail by the jihadists.
Submit to their dictate and pay the Islamic tax,
or see their village looted.
All of this was destroyed and rebuilt.
There,
There were thousands and everything was destroyed.
Moussatolo is deputy mayor of the commune of Kassa.
He comes to support the inhabitants in their reconstruction.
There are onions here.
Everything is ruined.
Here,
there were a thousand.
They stole everything they could.
And the rest,
They burned it.
The jihadists also want to eliminate anything that does not correspond to their fundamentalist vision of religion.
In 2012,
in Timbuktu,
spaces classified as world heritage sites,
They attacked the mausoleum of Muslim saints and tombstones.
They also smashed tribal art statuettes.
These treasures,
Mali is full of them.
Many residents here practice a form of Islam mixed with animism.
In Bamako,
the capital of Mali,
A French collector passionate about his works of art. First tries to preserve them.
Richard Pierron opened this gallery six months ago.
This is for the future catalog that I hope to be able to release around mid-June.
That's my wish, anyway.
This catalog will be sent to its customers,
especially to major auction houses.
But Richard also has a private collection,
exceptional pieces that escaped destruction.
He keeps them in a secret location.
This is a small part of what I can have here in Bamako.
His collection reached 13,000 pieces.
There are so many typologies.
That,
These are Ovon typologies.
It's also an Ovon mask.
That,
It's new.
He is fabulous.
So.
The superb masks from Korea, too.
We can immediately guess that it is a sheep.
These treasures,
Richard collected them from all corners of West Africa,
when it was still safe to move around.
Because of the war,
There are many such objects that have been destroyed.
It's permanent now.
NOW,
it is permanent as soon as we consider that they are evil objects,
for a number of people anyway.
And to avoid having any worries,
There are quite a few villages that are parting with their belongings.
It's very sad,
What.
so it disappears,
It's burnt, often.
In my opinion,
It is very sad.
Really,
I am quite saddened by all this.
Many pieces come from the Augon region.
Ah,
the Augon family,
Me,
I really appreciate it,
many of the Augon.
Today threatened by Islamists,
The cliff is the last bulwark against the jihadists in the plain.
Only a few corridors would allow them to access the plateau.
SO,
Hammer and his men protect them at the risk of their lives.
Five months ago,
Jihadists attempted an incursion through this passage.
20 people or 24 like that,
we are here.
Before nightfall,
The Dozos climb to the top of this promontory in order to spot jihadists who might attempt to use this access corridor.
It was in this camp that Hammer's unit was located during this attack.
More monks than us.
And there were no injuries on your side.
There were injuries.
There were injuries, there were injuries.
There were deaths too.
Oh, right, yes.
During the assault,
Hammer lost seven of his men.
But we,
we never claimed.
Even we,
we are all dead.
We will die together.
Because here,
This is our area.
Here,
this is our area,
king's daughter.
When you have left your area,
where did you do, we will do everything.
So the military doesn't come.
What should we do,
we had to remember something else.
Anyway,
We,
we are tired.
Very tired,
but we claimed.
Since my birth,
I never complained.
That's why I was named Hammer.
Little Hammer,
typed, Big Rock.
The Dozo are preparing to bivouac.
At night,
They must be extra careful to avoid being spotted.
Bashir,
the villager who supplies them,
came back to prepare the evening meal.
The smoking room,
you have to put it here.
SO,
like that,
in distance,
some distances,
We don't see the effect.
Oh yes.
Yes.
During the night,
light is prohibited.
SO,
to smoke too,
we're going to break and smoke.
So.
Anyway,
cigarettes,
it's forbidden at night,
during...
Yes,
We're going to break.
We have to act quickly.
I had seen it.
He's going to give it to me like that.
Right on the rock.
Just like that.
The rifle,
always in hand.
We arrive at Kassa.
The capital of the commune continues to resist jihadist raids.
As is customary,
before entering it,
The dozos must remove their hunting outfits and magic amulets.
Yes,
so we've already seen each other.
Because when,
SO,
for us,
Clothing is prohibited in the squares.
Downright,
SO,
women,
The kids will make our outfit for this.
They talk about it, they talk about it,
Yes.
For over a year,
Kassa's children are deprived of school.
The teachers fled after the last attack.
The classrooms now serve as temporary accommodation for hunters.
Hammer finds Moussa Tolo,
the deputy mayor.
Oh,
my major,
Hello, hello, how are you?
And the young people,
It's okay, everyone's fine, there's no problem, everything's fine,
everyone is fine,
No problem.
God bless you.
You are our only protectors.
You are the sentinels of the homeland.
The jihadists attempted to enter Kassa six times.
But thanks to Marteau and Odozo,
they failed.
The state doesn't listen to you
or he doesn't know what's going on
If,
the State is aware.
He's just afraid to come here because the area is really infested with jihadists.
The state is afraid to come here.
Even the mayor of the town is not there.
He left for Koro.
Moussatolo is the only representative of the Malian state who has not deserted his post.
Abandoned by his superiors,
he turned to the Haugon.
Good morning.
The traditional chief to discuss the economic and security problems plaguing the hamlet.
They took away all the cattle that were grazing.
When they steal your animals,
what do they do with it,
Who knows what they do with it?
Probably eat them.
After stealing them,
They certainly sell them too.
When they find some,
They resell them afterwards.
We, the farmers,
our bank,
it's the oxen,
goats and sheep.
We have no other riches.
The price of a beef is equivalent to 6 months of the average Malian salary.
With 68 million head of cattle,
Mali's livestock population is 9 times that of France.
The center of the country provides 90%
beef from the region.
Mali,
Senegal,
Ivory Coast,
Burkina Faso.
But the war completely destabilized this pillar of the economy.
Here,
It is becoming more and more complicated to feed oneself.
In Bandiagara,
the main city of Ogon Country,
The 20,000 inhabitants are hit hard by the meat shortage.
At the market,
The Butchers' business is slowing down.
My little brother came at 6am to tell me that the butcher was out of meat.
So far,
I didn't have any meat.
He went to look for it elsewhere,
So I'm waiting for him here.
We are suffering,
You know.
The scarcity of meat has pushed up prices.
Plus 25%
in 3 years.
That's 3000 francs.
So, a kilo of redhead's assistant,
It is...
3,000 francs.
That is 4.60 euros per kilo,
two days of average salary.
1,500.
But since he is an old man,
so I give him 1,250.
2,000 kilos.
Otherwise, it's 1,500.
As he is an old man,
so I give him...
Cheaper.
So.
Faced with the difficulties encountered by the population,
Butchers are almost no longer making any margin.
Before,
we win very well.
But now,
we win, not.
We still work,
but we win, nothing.
We don't want to leave our work.
NOW,
That's it.
Half of the market's butcher shops have closed.
But Amadou Traoré's is holding firm.
His father,
Camia,
is the president of the Butchers' Corporation.
In the family,
We have been doing this job from father to son since 1942.
And we have never seen such a crisis.
Before the war...
Amadou bought around twenty oxen a week.
Today,
He's been looking for some for five days.
But in town,
A man offers me some for sale.
There,
How much do you say? 390,000.
390,000 for 10,000 MP
to pay 385,000.
Drop,
drop.
I take 310,000.
315,000.
325,
That's good 380,000.
The dealer resists.
He took all the risks to go and buy it in the bush and he doesn't want to sell it off cheap.
Even where we speak,
It's very expensive there.
If you left too,
another person will pay.
It's difficult and it's risky too.
It's risky, it's risky.
All right.
Because there is too much insecurity.
But all that,
We,
we often go out to search.
There is not even any data.
In the walls,
we can't find it.
We find one,
only one.
Oh, good, yes.
Other days,
I moved more than 26 kilometers.
You just find that.
The conflict,
we just have to finish.
This is the only way.
We,
We only want peace.
Everyone saw nothing,
we found talking,
even the soul,
even the mind.
We stay as before.
Before,
yourself,
you come to Banyangala,
It's very good.
You eat as you want,
you sleep as you want,
you leave as you want,
you come as you want.
NOW,
it must also be said,
He only has to decrease one foot.
You will come back,
I imagine, I am,
I am.
Always Very,
very,
my daughter.
If he can no longer buy animals,
Amadou is in turn at risk of closing up shop.
Samba,
his younger son,
would have liked to break with family tradition and do a different job than that of his ancestors.
But the war put an end to his dream.
It's a bit of a job.
I am a rapper.
These are traditional reports.
Samba,
34 years old,
has been rapping since he was 16.
Before 2016,
He gave concerts in front of hundreds of people.
Today,
his only audience,
some young people from the neighborhood.
Since then, the war has returned,
I couldn't do a concert.
We were scared,
because there are threats.
We can organize a concert,
The bad guys can come in and attack us.
In these words,
Samba is worried because the war against the jihadists is turning into an ethnic conflict.
Samba
is Fulani,
An ethnic group present in 15 West African countries and traditionally very involved in butchery and livestock farming.
Today,
The people are caught between the jihadists,
the military and farmers.
Most of the people are semi-nomadic.
At the beginning of the dry season,
They migrate with their herds to the southern pastures.
But since the war,
The state no longer manages livestock transhumance corridors.
Result,
the oxen destroy part of the crops,
triggering conflicts between farmers and herdsmen.
When animals go down without superego,
There are also disputes over fields.
So, all the time,
These are conflicts.
For some time now,
The skins were under a lot of pressure from the administration.
And we take you,
we lock you up.
And the breeder has a schedule to be locked up.
So instead of being locked up,
he prefers to pay the million to get out.
Indeed,
Malian justice,
often corrupt,
makes them pay astronomical fines.
This resentment,
a Fulani exploited it to rally his fellow men to the jihadist cause.
This man,
This is Amadou Koufa.
To seduce them,
he named his group Katiba du Massina,
A reference to this golden age, when the Fulani caliphate of Massina dominated central Mali in the 19th century.
I take this opportunity to thank God for allowing me to see the day when thousands of Fulani joined the jihadists to fight in the path of God until martyrdom.
Amadou Koufa began his career as a preacher in the 1990s.
The audio cassettes of his sermons were a hit among the Fulani.
It's in Mopti,
the capital of the region where he recorded his sermons,
in the studios of Radio, Sagan,
the most listened to in the area.
Today a radio host,
Ousmane Koïta was the jihadist leader's sound engineer.
We stopped these cassettes in the market.
They are rarely found nowadays, because almost all the hunters of these tapes have been arrested. Once,
twice.
Before Amadou Koufa became an outlaw in 2012,
Ousmane recorded his sermons every week for three years.
He remembers one of them,
particularly explicit.
You who are marginalized,
you who are really robbed, feet and bothered by the wearer of Malian uniform,
You will no longer be taxed or given information,
nor other taxes,
absolutely nothing.
Come with me.
Words that hit the mark at the time.
It is true that the malicious insistence had annoyed the population.
A lot,
a lot,
a lot of ink.
They immediately followed his call and left.
With the influx of new recruits,
Amadou Koufa's group has increased its influence over central Mali.
Mopti is located at the confluence of the Niger and Bani rivers,
A strategic location for river trade between the North and the South of Mali.
Since 2019,
only the river separates Mopti from the areas controlled by the jihadists.
If the exchanges between the two banks have not stopped,
in front,
Sharia law applies.
When they cross the river,
women must now wear the black hijab,
at the risk of being beaten.
The thieves,
them,
expose themselves to having their hands and feet cut off.
Four repentant jihadists who lived on the other side of the river agreed to meet us.
All are Fulani and say they joined the ranks of the Islamists because they were persecuted.
This former shepherd even saw his village attacked by the Malian army and ozo hunters.
They say that all Fulani are jihadists, but that is not the case.
So they attack our villages,
kill women,
2 or 3 year old grandchildren who are unable to defend themselves.
And even old women who don't know how to handle a rifle.
And during the attacks,
you have parents who were killed.
Yes.
Once enlisted,
Those who want to fight must buy their own weapons and motorcycles.
Some have spent up to 1,800 euros to equip themselves.
Everyone participates.
To camp life, nomad.
Me,
during these three years,
I went out fighting almost all the time.
But since I am a shepherd,
I also took care of animals.
So when I was going to fight,
someone replaced me to leather the animals.
There were many cows,
often more than 1,500 head of cattle.
Sometimes, more,
sometimes less.
Among these animals,
There were also those that we had taken from our enemies.
Those who go to war are entitled to their share of the spoils.
But the emir takes 60% of it
to finance the operations of the Katiba.
For this ex-fighter,
This distribution is unfair.
And he lets his boss know.
Before coming,
I was not satisfied with the justice of the whites,
And I am no more so with you.
So now,
let me go.
Like that,
you can do as you see fit.
But the main reason for their departure,
It is the austere lifestyle imposed.
Jihadists apply a Salafist interpretation of the Quran.
I couldn't do what I wanted.
I was afraid to say what I thought.
Because if I did,
I was called a hypocritical Muslim.
All of this was part of their application of Sharia law.
Everything you do must be validated by them.
Even if it doesn't suit you,
you have to do it.
Whether you like it or not,
They indoctrinate you.
Above all,
They were told to change the way they pray.
They force you to put your hands like this to pray.
Were you asked to become a Salafist?
Yes.
Me,
I am malevolent.
They wanted to change that,
but I didn't agree,
so I left the group.
Practiced here for centuries,
Malequism advocates a tolerant reading of the Koran,
unlike Salafism,
imported to Mali in the 1980s,
by preachers,
originating from the Gulf countries.
Disappointed at not having found the just society they imagined,
all returned to their village,
with their former neighbors,
often of different ethnicities.
When I returned home,
when the Dogons saw me,
at first,
They were afraid of me.
But after some time,
Those I live with were no longer afraid.
They look at me now as if I had done nothing,
and that they had nothing to reproach me for.
They got used to me.
The Fulani and the Dogon will always need each other.
For example,
to cultivate fields,
build houses,
dig wells,
The Dogons do it best.
For animal breeding,
The Fulani are more gifted.
Persecuted,
notably by Malian soldiers,
Hundreds of thousands of Fulani have left central Mali.
Some have found refuge in neighboring countries,
as in Mauritania,
the most stable state in the Sahel.
The Mbera refugee camp is home to 67,000 people.
Most of them are Tuaregs who fled jihadists in northern Mali in 2012.
But the latest arrivals are all Fulani,
like Birguisso.
A year ago,
This traditional chief fled his village,
after being threatened by a Malian soldier.
The soldier told me...
I swear I won't tell you twice.
I heard that the Fulani are killing us,
that the jihadists kill us.
And in this case,
We will kill all the Fulani.
So I called the sub-prefect of the jurisdiction and he told us not to move from our house.
He told us that no one would hurt us.
Despite these calls for help,
no state authority takes Birguisso seriously.
The following Friday.
Soldiers came to the village.
They surrounded him first.
It was between 1 and 2 p.m.
Then,
They entered the village.
They attacked everyone who was sitting.
They entered the rooms and dragged the sick people out of their homes.
They killed 7 people.
The Fulani of the village are afraid.
Birguiso then urgently organized the departure of 1,000 families to Mauritania.
Today,
where I am,
we live in peace.
I thank God.
For now,
even if we chartered a plane,
I won't go back.
What they did to us will remain etched in our memories.
They murdered people.
Birguiso and his villagers will not return to Mali until their safety is assured.
Because here...
In addition to United Nations food aid,
Fulani refugees like him can resume an almost normal life,
cultivate land,
raise their animals,
and even go to school,
take care of the populations to gain their support.
This is part of the overall strategy of the Mauritanian state.
The country has also extensively restructured its army following around ten jihadist attacks.
To the heart of the capital,
Today it is considered the most professional in the region.
One of the main air bases in Mauritania is located in Attar,
at the gates of the Sahara.
On the tarmac,
devices that seem to come from another age,
like this antique DC-3 from the 50s,
or these Brazilian-made fighters.
Despite their rudimentary appearance,
They are perfectly suited to the war being waged here.
Colonel Taleb is in charge of this squadron.
This is the Super Tucano.
This aircraft has double the range compared to the Tucano, with very powerful armament.
And we have the ability to put different types of weaponry on it.
We have two of these built-ins,
electric machine guns and two rocket launchers.
The AU-7A.
You can put rockets in it. 70 mm.
It's for vehicles, it's for vehicles.
Often,
The choice of weaponry depends on the target.
These fighter jets have the advantage of being very maneuverable and can land on rough runways in the middle of the desert.
But before you start hunting,
The Mauritanian Air Force must uncover the menus.
And that,
This is the mission of reconnaissance aircraft.
Permanently,
These Cessna Caravans monitor the 2000 km of borders that Mauritania shares with its neighbor,
Mali.
In total,
450,000 km² of desert,
80%
of France.
Lieutenant Youssouf is a sensor operator.
It controls the high-definition cameras that allow you to see up to 20 km.
For them,
Jihadists and traffickers are closely linked.
This country,
among the poorest in the world,
did not skimp on the means.
Each monitoring system costs a million dollars and allows the soil to be examined,
in all circumstances.
And above all,
thanks to the thermal sensor,
Lieutenant Youssouf sees the vehicle tracks in the sand,
even several hours after their passage.
Because the desert is not so empty.
Nomads pitch their tents there and gold miners exploit the abundant gold in the region.
Here,
one of their trucks transporting equipment.
If they spot any weapons,
Lieutenant Youssouf alerts the command.
It is the high-ranking officers who order the strikes.
Over the past three years,
Colonel Taleb and the pilots of the Attar base
intercepted 25 pick-ups belonging to traffickers or jihadists,
as in this video from January 2019,
exclusive images.
That day,
The Mauritanian army destroys four jihadist pickup trucks.
Wait,
They are on the fourth.
Don't let the fourth one slip away.
Don't worry,
I'm not going to let go of him.
The reorganization of the army also concerns ground troops.
In 2009,
the State founds, the GSI,
special intervention groups.
Commandos specialized in the fight against terrorism and who were trained by France.
Eight units of 200 men monitor the border with Mali.
Attention
work for the fight,
to your posts.
This section of 80 soldiers leaves for a three-day patrol.
Their pickup trucks are equipped with heavy machine guns.
The area of operation covers 18,000 km².
To cover as much ground as possible,
The 4x4s are deployed over a 5 km wide strip.
Every 500 meters,
they stop.
Every thorny bush is a potential hiding place for an ambush enemy.
Move,
move,
Move. Signal to your friend to cleave you.
Tell him to go through the trees and move quickly.
To effectively fight against jihadists,
The army also relies on human intelligence.
Hey there,
eh,
come here, come here
don't move forward any further.
How are you
It's okay. And in the village,
everything is fine.
I hope there is no problem.
Hello to you,
Come a little closer now.
Shepherds constantly roam the savannah.
They are a valuable source of information.
You saw new faces,
Nobody. Everything is fine.
Yes, thank God,
everything is fine.
Okay,
Alright,
you can go.
A jihadist group would not go unnoticed among these nomads.
SO,
to maintain their confidence,
The soldiers bring them medicine once a month.
And every time,
They are entitled to a welcome party.
When the military arrives in a village,
We welcome them like that.
It is a warm welcome, of brotherhood,
of friendship and love.
For 12 years,
The presence of the GSI has radically changed the lives of its inhabitants,
like that of this cattle owner.
There's no denying it.
Since the army has been here,
there is no more animal theft.
Never.
Not even a rooster.
And at night,
we can sleep now.
Look at,
Our cows come and go on their own and there is no more animal theft.
The state has not put all its money on security.
To avoid a Malian scenario, where some residents feel abandoned,
the Mauritanian government
also created a community police force,
present in the most remote parts of the territory and traveling only on the back of dromedaries.
Today,
25 gendarmes are preparing to leave for an expedition lasting several days,
a camel trek.
Look at,
he is with arba,
Catch him
look at
You are with Ahmed Salem,
Dio and Mohamed Val.
They are under the orders of Colonel El Khalil.
Before leaving,
take a reserve.
This will allow me to do the whole day,
otherwise, from here until noon.
With three gorges of water, there, of course,
and with a real camel driver.
He can do it all day.
With just three sips, I assure you that with two liters of water,
at most,
two liters of water,
it can be 24 hours.
Oh yes,
and the camel,
we don't talk about it,
it hurts.
The two gourds,
If they are filled with water,
they can do up to 10 days,
in the middle of the desert.
If it can travel 65 km in a day and carry 400 kg of load,
The dromedary remains a recalcitrant animal and difficult to guide.
SO,
to be part of the camel corps,
Two conditions are required.
Having been nomadic and knowing the region perfectly,
its populations and their dialect.
You've been doing this for a long time, so yes,
Yes.
How many years has the year been?
I am a former nomad.
The primary mission of these experienced men,
to get in touch with people and listen to their problems.
How are you
Where are you from?
I'm going to get some water.
Where is it?
to drilling?
Water supply is the main concern of the inhabitants.
Sayyed Gabra's is no closer.
I'm from there.
And there is no water
No.
Damn, no more water.
Lack of water can quickly become a source of conflict between breeders.
SO,
in case of a well, silted up,
The colonel passes on the information.
Advance,
advance.
This is part of his mission,
as well as its intelligence activities.
Good morning,
we're not going to ask you for a sheep,
We just need some information.
At each meeting,
the same questions,
the condition of the wells and suspicious movements.
Good,
I asked him a lot of questions,
He says everything is normal,
He did not notice anything abnormal.
So, okay,
you can go.
There is no water.
There is no water there, No,
No.
No,
There is a well in front.
This is where we will camp.
Inshallah.
It is even the camel drivers who are responsible for maintaining the wells.
In recent years,
The Mauritanian state and the European Union have also financed the drilling of hundreds of new wells,
allowing the population not to feel abandoned.
And this policy is effective.
Have you ever reported the presence of jihadists?
Yes of course,
we have already seen some.
It has happened several times already,
and the authorities were informed.
In some cases,
they are ordinary citizens,
but in others,
They are indeed terrorists.
Anything can happen.
When we see suspicious movements,
we report them directly.
The other effect of the presence of these wells
to fix the populations in these desert areas,
which could otherwise become sanctuaries for jihadists from Mali.